Common Experience collection 11.200.CommonExperience
University Archives, Texas State University
Common Experience collection
2004-2020
University Archives, Texas State University https://www.univarchives.txstate.edu/
Texas State University; Texas State University--San Marcos
11.200.CommonExperience
8.33 Linear Feet Foldered items and books in six letter hollinger boxes, one legal hollinger box, and one carton; posters in one flat 11x17 box and two flat 16x20 boxes.
4.45 Gigabytes
Each year since 2004, the Common Experience events bring students together to read and engage with a powerful text, and explore related themes in University Seminar classes. Collection consists of background and planning materials, press releases, posters, calendars of events, as well as each year's book.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically and grouped by Common Experience theme with the exception of the Planning records series which contains materials that covers 2005 to 2020.
Historical note
The Common Experience tradition began with the 2004-05 academic year. It "brings students together to read and engage with a powerful text, explore related themes in University Seminar classes, write responses and reactions to the text in writing courses, participate in related symposia with scholarly panels, hear renowned and respected speakers address the topic, see films related to the Common Experience theme, explore the experience by way of the fine arts, engage in informal discussions in residence halls and coffee shops, and extend the exploration via the avenues of their own choosing." Beginning in 2007, the Lyndon Baines Johnson Distinguished Lecture Series was held in conjunction with the Common Experience.
[Taken from Common Experience Website.]
Historical note
Each year since 2004, diverse groups of faculty, staff, and students have created distinctive experiences for our campus and community, with presentations by some of the world's most important voices on the issues of our time. Speakers have included poet Maya Angelou, filmmaker Spike Lee, writer Isabel Allende, broadcast journalist Soledad O'Brien, filmmaker Robert Rodriguez, Adm. William McRaven, attorney Bryan Stevenson, astronaut José Hernández, and Oscar/Grammy-winner Common. In fall 2020, the Common Experience presented live online events with John Quiñones of ABC News (and host of What Would You Do?) and U.S. Olympic gymnast Laurie Hernandez. Additionally, there have been many special events, such as Innovation Week in 2018, which offered 50-plus events over five days for learning and engaging with new ideas on campus.
Common Experience proposals should establish strong connections to a theme and events that cross academic boundaries, creating junctions for Academic Affairs and Student Affairs.
[Taken from Common Experiance email].
Related Materials
Beginning in 2007, the Lyndon Baines Johnson Distinguished Lecture Series was held in conjunction with the Common Experience. See 11.200.LBJ Distinguished Lectures.
Scope and Contents
Collection consists of background materials, such as descriptions of the event and proposals for themes. Also includes materials used and saved from each theme, such as newspaper clippings and press releases, posters, calendars of events, etc. Each year's theme also featured a book, and these are kept with the series. Each series various in documentation; after 2017, the documentation is limited.
Acquisition Information
Information not available.
Index Terms
Places
Talks (Speeches)
- Planning records, 2003-2017
  Scope and Contents
  Materials in this series consist of primarily planning documents, theme proposals, grant applications, and funding information. There is a small amount of contracts and correspondence with speakers and performance groups as well as meeting notes. Organized by year and theme, the documents are not consistent in coverage, with some years more robust in documentation than others. Also includes event lists for each year. Contains one folder of clippings that have articles about Common Experience events and advertisements.
  - Planning records, undated
    - Background materials, Summary of the common experience (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Digital files, 2004-2017
    Digital files including Word documents, PDFs, JPGs, TIFs, Powerpoint, and Excel sheets related to the planning and funding of the Common Experience events. Includes correspondence to speakers, grant applications, teaching guides, posters, a team manual, and digital photographs of the events.
    - CE - Chris Frost papers, initial conversation papers, 2017
    - CE, 2004-2005
    - CE, 2005-2006
    - CE, 2006-2007
    - CE, 2007-2008
    - CE, 2008-2009
    - CE, 2009-2010
    - CE, 2010-2011
    - CE, 2011-2012
    - CE, 2012-2013
    - CE, 2013-2014
    - CE, 2014-2015
    - CE, 2015-2016
    - CE, 2016-2017
    - CE, 2017-2018
    - CE Information, 2008-2017
    - CE Manual, 2013-2017
    - CE Posters 2004-2017
    - Common Experience Photos, 2005-2016
    - Manual for Common Experience, 2013-2017
- Posters, 2006-2018
  - Posters, 2005 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    One poster from 2005: Candlestein play.
  - Poster sketchbooks, 2006-2009 (Box 9)
    Four sketchbooks with posters and clippings pasted to the pages. One sketchbook removed from binding.
  - Posters, 2006-2008 (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
    Loose posters from Common Experience events Protest and Dissent as well as Water Planet.
  - Posters, 2008-2016 (Box 10, Folder 1-9, Map-case 19)
    Loose posters from Common Experience events. One oversized poster from Civic Responsibility and the Legacy of LBJ in verticle file.
  - Posters, 2016-2018 (Box 6, Folder 2-3)
    Loose posters from Common Experience events.
- Hatred, 2004-2005
  Biographical / Historical
  'Explorations on Night and the Challenge of Hatred-A Common Experience' is a year-long initiative of Texas State University-San Marcos designed to cultivate a 'common intellectual conversation' across the campus, to enhance student participation in the intellectual life of the campus, and to foster a sense of community across our entire campus and extended community. By examining the deep roots of hatred, we may expose the manner in which hate-based actions can be couched in the name of good-while inflicting harm. Through honest dialogue, we may become more aware of the role that hatred plays in our lives, our community, our world and our collective history.
  --from Common Experience Website.
  Nagy, Tibor P., Jr.; Shepard, Judy; Elliott, Jane; Wiesel, Elie
  - Theme, 2004-2005; Theme description, list of events, clippings. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Student work, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 1-4)
    Student work presumably from the University Seminar in Fall 2004. Consists of three scrapbooks and one reflection journal.
  - Night by Elie Wiesel, 2004-2005 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Courage, 2005-2006
  The 2005-2006 Common Experience engages students in a campus-wide discussion of 'Courage' as it is examined in the Summer Reading book If I Die in a Combat Zone by Tim O'Brien.
  The themes and emotions that O'Brien explores in the context of Vietnam are the themes and emotions of human life: friendship, patriotism, duty, sacrifice, leadership, innocence and experience, good and evil, humanity and inhumanity. Arguably the central theme in much of O'Brien's work - a theme he explores with passion and honesty - is Courage. Courage offers a relevant, challenging, and inspiring theme for the 2005-2006 Common Experience.
  --from Common Experience Webiste
  Lee, Spike; O'Brien, Tim
  - Theme, 2005-2006; Explanation of theme, list of events, press releases, clippings, event posters, play program. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Student work, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    Student work presumably from the University Seminar in Fall 2005. Consists of one scrapbook.
  - Promotional materials, 2005-2006 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - If I Die in a Combat Zone: Box Me Up and Ship Me Home by Tim O'Brien, 2005-2006 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Protest & Dissent, 2006-2007
  The 2006-2007 Common Experience will engage in a campus-wide discussion of 'Protest and Dissent: Listening to the Voice(s) of America.' It has at its center the idea that the United States of America is a heterogeneous nation, one with many voices. Rather than the idea that we as a nation have only one perspective or belief, students are encouraged to explore the idea that many people view many ideas in very different ways, and that as students and Americans it is their responsibility to recognize that others have a right to dissent from both their own personal beliefs and the beliefs of those in power. Further, they also have the right to dissent from others' beliefs as well. How we respond to and listen to those whose beliefs are different than our own is, however, key.
  --from Common Experience Website
  Valdez, Louis; Carlos, John P.; Olmos, Edward James
  - Theme, 2006-2007; Explanation of theme, list of events, news articles. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Promotional materials, 2006-2007 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Zoot Suit and Other Plays by Luis Valdez, 2006-2007 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Water Planet, 2007-2008
  As a theme for the Common Experience, the subject of water has particular relevance for our university. The unique, spring-fed San Marcos River that runs through campus is a constant visual reminder of the many dimensions and roles that water plays in our lives. The nexus of the Common Experience parallels this literal flow: it fosters students' confluent thinking where discovery in one area will lead them to discovery in another.
  Earle, Sylvia A.; Brockovich, Erin
  - Theme, 2007-2008; Explanation of theme, list of events, clippings. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Promotional materials, 2007-2008 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Goodbye to a River: A Narrative by John Graves, 2007-2008 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Civic Responsibility and the Legacy of LBJ, 2008-2009
  August 27, 2008, marks the 100th anniversary of the birth of Lyndon B. Johnson, 36th President of the United States and the most distinguished alumnus of Texas State. As part of the LBJ Centennial Celebration, the 2008-2009 Common Experience theme, 'Civic Responsibility and the Legacy of LBJ,' focuses on Johnson's devotion to public service and his contributions that continue to impact American society.
  Young, Andrew; Bullion, John L.; Robb, Lynda Bird; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973; Nugent, Luci Baines Johnson
  - Theme, 2008-2009; Explanation of theme, list of events, clippings. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - LBJ reader, 2008-2009 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
    Two draft readers.
  - Promotional materials, 2008-2009 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Lyndon B. Johnson and the Transformation of American Politics by John L. Bullion, 2008-2009 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Whole Mind: Crossing Boundaries and Disciplines, 2009-2010
  As a theme for the Common Experience, 'The Whole Mind: Crossing Boundaries of Disciplines' has captured the imagination of a wide spectrum of the university and San Marcos community. From such diverse disciplines as marketing, art and design, biology, literature, physics, education, theatre, philosophy, communication studies, finance and economics, music, social work, and mathematics, faculty and students are intrigued with the possibilities inherent in this theme. Moreover, local community groups in San Marcos, from the chamber of commerce to local arts groups, are making connections to the theme as well.
  Pink, Daniel H.; Robinson, Ken, Sir
  - Theme, 2009-2010; Explanation of theme, list of events, clippings. Portraits of the Artist's Mind, a program by Wayne O'Quin, Juilliard (DVD). Sir Ken Robinson Creavity and Education 2010 (DVD). (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Promotional materials, 2009-2010 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - A Whole New Mind: Why Right-Brainers WIll Rule the Future by Daniel H. Pink, 2009-2010 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - The Whole Mind resources, 2009-2010 (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
    Removed from binder. Articles and readings organized by topic.
- Sustainability: Science, Policy, and Opportunity, 2010-2011
  The Common Experience theme for 2010-2011 is 'Sustainability: Science, Policy, and Opportunity,' an interdisciplinary theme that affects all students, staff, faculty, and administrators of Texas State, as well as the San Marcos community. Because of the integrative nature of the problems that humanity faces, the only way in which these problems can be realistically addressed is through interdisciplinary dialogue, outreach, and education. The capacity of humanity to adapt in a dynamic world that is constantly presenting new challenges is essential in the 21st century.
  Watson, Paul; Beavan, Colin
  - Theme, 2010-2011; Explanation of theme, list of events, clippings. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - No Impact Man: The Adventures of a Guilty Liberal Who Attempts to Save the Planet and Discoveries He Makes About Himself and Our Way of Life in the Process, by Colin Beavan, 2010-2011 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Freedoms: The First Amendment, 2011-2012
  The Common Experience theme for 2011-2012 is 'Freedoms: The First Amendment,' an interdisciplinary theme that affects all departments, offices, and organizations at Texas State—thus allowing for a cross-disciplinary, cross-campus, and multi-organizational conversation. The First Amendment protects the basic freedoms of religion, expression (speech), press, and assembly. Discussion and examination of the First Amendment will allow students, faculty, and staff to understand the Founding Fathers' intentions regarding basic freedoms.
  --from the Common Experience Website
  McConnell, Aaron; O'Brien, Soledad; Hennessey, Jonathan
  - Theme, 2011-2012; Explanation of theme, list of events, clippings. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Promotional materials, 2011-2012 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - The United States Constitution: A Graphic Adaptation, written by Jonathan Hennessey, art by Aaron McConnell, 2011-2012 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- A Global Odyssey: Exploring Our Connections to the Changing World, 2012-2013
  The Common Experience theme for 2012-2013 is 'A Global Odyssey: Exploring Our Connections to the Changing World,' an interdisciplinary theme that affects all departments, offices, and organizations at Texas State—thus allowing for a cross-disciplinary, cross-campus, and multi-organizational conversation.
  - Theme, 2012-2013; Explanation of theme, list of events, planning. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Where Am I Wearing?: A Global Tour to the Countries, Factories, and People that Make Our Clothes, by Kelsey Timmerman, 2012-2013 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Minds Matter: Exploring Mental Health and Illness, 2013-2014
  The 2013-14 Common Experience program will explore how perceptions of mental health and illness affect our thinking, laws, actions, and quality of life. The upcoming theme of 'Minds Matter: Exploring Mental Health and Illness' will encourage students, faculty, staff and community members to recognize the importance of balancing human rights, freedoms, and creativity with effective social services, business practices, educational programs, and healthcare in support of mental health. Participants will develop a better understanding of the causes of recent events said to be related to psychiatric conditions, while they increase their knowledge of the worldwide consequences of mental health and illness.
  Kennedy, Patrick J. (Patrick Joseph); Hall, Melanie (Melanie Whitley); Szabo, Ross
  - Theme, 2013-2014; Explanation of theme, press releases. Lecturer: Patrick Kennedy. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Promotional materials, 2013-2014 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Behind Happy Faces: Taking Charge of Your Mental Health: A Guide for Young Adults, by Ross Szabo and Melanie Hall, 2013-2014 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Exploring Democracy's Promise: From Segregation to Integration, 2014-2015
  The 2014-2015 Common Experience theme is inspired by the 50th anniversary of the desegregation of Texas State University, known in 1963 as Southwest Texas State College. In January of 1963 Judge Ben H. Rice ruled that SWT could not deny admission to an African-American student based solely on race. After the ruling, in the fall of 1963, 18-year-old Dana Jean Smith, a graduate of Anderson High School in Austin, Texas, enrolled at SWT. The registrar personally assisted Smith in registering along with four other African American students — Georgia Hoodye, Gloria Odoms, Mabeleen Washington, and Helen Jackson.
  This Common Experience theme explores the trials of segregation and the impact of integration, raising the question of how we internalize change in this 50-year celebration of the desegregation of Texas State. A closer exploration of desegregation reveals a long and difficult struggle to achieve one of modern democracy's great promises, equal access to a quality education. Specifically, we use this 50-year anniversary of the desegregation of our institution as an opportunity to examine issues related to equal access to higher education and the role of laws, litigation, and civil rights movements in helping students obtain higher education. This theme also makes a connection to the 2008-2009 Common Experience theme, "Civic Responsibility and the Legacy of LBJ," celebrating our most famous alumnus, Lyndon Baines Johnson. Bringing LBJ into the conversation emphasizes the role he played in making these changes happen and helps build pride in Texas State and its graduates.
  Moody, Anne
  - Theme, 2014-2015; Explanation of theme, list of events, common reading program. DVD of common reading video. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Promotional material, 2014-2015 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Coming of Age in Mississippi, by Anne Moody, 2014-2015 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Bridged Through Stories: Shared Heritage of the United States and Mexico, an Homage to Dr. Tomás Rivera, 2015-2016
  Texas State University's mission statement includes the shared values of "diversity of people and ideas." Since 2011, Texas State has held the designation of Hispanic Serving Institution (HSI), which means that at least 25 percent of its undergraduate enrollment is Hispanic. President Denise Trauth rightfully pointed to the challenge of recognizing the service aspect of HSI when she stated, "It is not enough to recruit talented students from all ethnicities — we must also continue to retain those students and see that they graduate."
  The theme of "Bridged Through Stories: Shared Heritage of the United States and Mexico" will highlight the work and values of Tomás Rivera as well as those of others from all walks of life who have contributed to the fabric of our common understandings of the world. Through specific attention to connections between stories of Mexico and the United States, this theme will highlight multiple perspectives that contribute to community building, affirmations of identity, and collective struggles to make the world a more just place for everyone.
  Rodriguez, Robert (Robert Anthony); Rivera, Tomás
  - Theme, 2015-2016; Explanation of theme, list of events, programs, press releases. Lecture by Robert Rodriguez, screenwriter/director/producer. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Promotional materials, 2015-2016 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - …y no se lo tragó la tierra / …And the Earth Did Not Devour Him, by Tomás Rivera, 2015-2016 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Century of Conflict: Dialogues on the U.S. experience of war since 1917, 2016-2017
  Marlantes, Karl; McRaven, William (William Harry)
  - Theme, 2016-2017 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    Container Summary
    Information on theme, news releases, and notes.
  - Promotional materials, 2016-2017 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - What it is like to Go to War by Karl Marlantes, 2016-2017 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- The Search for Justice: Our response to crime in the 21st century, 2017-2018
  Crime and criminal justice are major civil rights issues of our time: the rights of victims, criminal defendants, prisoners, those in police custody, and ex-felons are considered to be under attack by different segments of society for various reasons. In addition, tensions exist around the criminalization of marginalized groups (including women, immigrants, those in the LGBTQIA communities, and so forth), the war on drugs, the war on terrorism, mass incarceration, and mass governmental surveillance. Central to this topic is the idea of fairness, which engages our students in thoughtful discussions that could have a lifetime impact.
  Through gaining a stronger comprehension of concepts of justice and crime, students will gain a greater appreciation of a core principle of their democratic system as it pertains to their own fields, as well as to their participation in the process of governance (both as citizens and future leaders). This theme helps students understand some of the more serious repercussions of decisions made by law enforcement, courts, parole boards, and even our elected representatives for both offenders and victims.
  Stevenson, Bryan; Nutt, Samantha
  - Theme, 2017-2018 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    Includes information on theme, news release, event list, and print out of speaker poster for Anthony Graves.
  - Just Mercy: A story of Justice and redemption by Bryan Stevenson, 2017-2018 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Innovation, 2018-2019
  Since its inception in 2004, the Common Experience has presented an academic theme each year at Texas State University. Events and activities have expanded far beyond the experiences of first-year students; the initiative has extended its impact across divisions — and to all levels — through cooperation and collaboration among students, faculty, staff, administration, and members of the community. The sustained success of the Common Experience has made Texas State a national leader in first-year experience (FYE) approaches and campus-wide collaborations.
  The key to this sustained success: Innovation.
  ..The 2018-19 Common Experience theme focuses on innovation as a means to engage students, faculty, staff, and the community/region in a conversation about the ideas and opportunities that will shape our future, here at Texas State and throughout the world — and beyond.
  This theme presents an opportunity not only for innovation to inspire a conversation but also for that conversation to inspire innovation. With eyes to the future, we have an opportunity to draw the connections between the world of innovation and Texas State while also raising Texas State's visibility and reputation in innovating the world...
  Innovation is sometimes simple and sometimes remarkably difficult. Major obstacles can hinder progress on any project in any discipline, whether inside a classroom or outside in fieldwork — both in education and the workplace. How we overcome those obstacles demonstrates yet another dimension to innovation.
  The world is rapidly changing, and this Common Experience theme aspires to immerse students in that change to become active participants in it.
  Many voices. One theme: Innovation.
  Eagleman, David; Brandt, Anthony K.; Hernández, José M., 1962-
  - Theme, 2018-2019 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    Press releases about Innovation week and speakers.
  - Promotional materials, 2018-2019 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - The Runaway Species: How Human Creativity Remakes the World by neuroscientist David Eagleman and composer Anthony Brandt, 2018-2019 (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Truth, 2019-2020
  During the 2019-2020 academic year, Texas State University students will become scholars of Truth. To fully and freely participate in the world, a core value of Texas State's mission statement, students should actively pursue truth and the complexity of its meaning. This pursuit is our Common Experience theme.